## Varun Totakura

(848) 667-6729 — varun.totakura@gmail.com — varuntotakura.github.io — Google Scholar @ZbVUfuYAAAAJ

## **Professional Summary**

Passionate Software/ML Engineer with over 4 years of professional experience. Developed ML/Active Learning algorithms as a Research Assistant while pursuing a Master's degree. Excellent team player and individual contributor with strong interpersonal skills, committed to achieving project objectives efficiently.

### **Technical Skills**

- Languages: Python, Go Lang, C, C++, Java, JavaScript, R
- Platforms: PyTorch, Tensorflow, HuggingFace, Apache Kafka, Altreyx, Qlik, Power BI, PySpark, Tableau, SnowFlake, OpenAI, GitHub, Agile Scrum
- Databases: MySQL, NoSQL
- Operating Systems: Windows, Linux
- Clouds: ServiceNow, Google Cloud, Microsoft Azure, AWS
- Tools: Microsoft AI Studio, Google Cloud Vertex AI, Spyder, Visual Studio, R Studio, Jira

## **Professional Experience**

#### Machine Learning Engineer - GRA, Florida State University, Tallahassee, FL

August 2022 - Present

- Analyzed the behavior of elderly individuals affected by Alzheimer's Disease and crafted an innovative architecture combining TCN, CNN, and GRU while reducing domain disparity enhanced it's performance by 35%.
- Predicted model correctness by leveraging Deep Learning techniques and working across approximately 10 diverse datasets totaling over 300,000 records.
- Engaged in Active Learning with Imperfect Oracles, implemented in an optimized fashion by leveraging parallel computing techniques to achieve a remarkable 24-fold reduction in execution time from 8 hours to just 20 minutes.
- Designed a Natural Language Processing solution utilizing BERT for Bug Localization by processing over 150,000 text records gathered from various social media sources and identifying precise bugs within code snippets.

#### Software Developer - Systems Engineer, Tata Consultancy Services, Hyderabad, India

July 2020 - July 2022

- Communicated with cross-functional teams to develop intelligent chatbots using Azure and Virtual Agent to streamline
  operations and enhance user interactions by fetching data from 9+ sources.
- Integrated ServiceNow with 5 types of external platforms using REST, SOAP, and Email in Agile methodology.
- Developed scalable ServiceNow integrations by automating various processes which significantly increased the productivity time by over 45%.
- Played a key role in a migration project, used integrations and automated flows to transfer over 1.5 million records of data within a short period.
- Ensured seamless data flow across multiple ServiceNow instances, as well as between ServiceNow and external platforms facilitating efficient operations reaching about 95% accuracy.
- Collaborated in the project's R&D endeavors by designing machine learning-driven automation, resulting in solutions that enhanced task efficiency by an impressive factor of 20.
- Served as a peer leader, monitoring team performance and implementing strategies that boosted individual performance by more than 5 fold.
- Researched Power Automate, Azure, and Google Cloud and revamped ServiceNow to include a robust history for developing consistency across 11 types of integrations.

#### Cyber Smart Intern, Telangana State Police, Hyderabad, India

September 2019 – October 2019

- Worked on enhancing the performance of facial recognition using Google Cloud Vertex AI by improving accuracy by 1.5 times.
- Explored the nefarious world of phishing, trojans, worms, SQL injections and tried to penetrate a safe virtual environment in 7 different ways.
- Utilized ML algorithms with Python to implement a malware detection system in a Windows environment which gave about 85% accuracy.

### Software Developer Intern, Johan Brown Pvt Ltd, Hyderabad, India

October 2016 – April 2017

• Studied data analysis and visualization, wielding powerful tools like Tableau to analyze patterns in 5000+ conference paper submissions.

- Implemented a diverse range of applications in Java, and JavaScript for design adjustment in more than 1500 ePub books
- Embraced the power of web scraping and automation using Python to automate the changes in ePub books which increased time efficiency by 15 times.

### **Research Publications**

<ul> <li>Active Learning with Imperfect Oracles using Text Data.</li> </ul>	TPAMI - Expected 2024
• MetaErr: Predicting Error Patterns in Deep Neural Networks using the Meta Model Data.	BMVC - Expected 2024
• Analysing the behavioural patterns in elderly people suffering with Alzheimer's Disease.	TACCESS - Expected 2024
• Master's Thesis - A Study on Deep Learning Models for Real World Applications.	August 2024
• Prediction of Transmittable Diseases Rate in a Location Using ARIMA and GARCH.	November 2021
• Improved Safety of Self-Driving Car using Voice Recognition through CNN.	October 2021
• Prediction of Stock Trend for Swing Trades using Long Short-Term Memory Neural Network	work Model. March 2020
<ul> <li>Prediction of Animal Vocal Emotions using Convolutional Neural Network.</li> </ul>	February 2020
• An Integrated Approach to Sentiment Analysis using Machine Learning Algorithms.	April 2020
• Published another 5 research papers and survey papers.	2019 - 2020

## **Awards and Achievements**

• Three times Star of the Month, Tata Consultancy Services.	2021 - 2022
• Five times On the Spot Awards, Tata Consultancy Services.	2021 - 2022
Learning Achievement Award, Tata Consultancy Services.	2021 - 2022
Ranked 2nd Topper in Academics, Guru Nanak Institutions.	2019
• Google Scholar - https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=ZbVUfuYAAAAJ	2019 - 2024
• ORCID ID - © https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5114-5205	2019 - 2024

# **Certifications and Trainings**

Completed Deep Learning Specialization taught by Andrew Ng and other instructors.	2020
• Completed altogether 10 Coursera courses on Machine Learning, Customer Analytics and more.	2020
• Ethical Hacking, IOT, and Web Development training by Imparta.	June 2019

## **Education**

# Florida State University, Tallahassee, Florida, United States

Master of Science in Computer Science (Thesis)

Jawaharlal Nehru Technological University - Guru Nanak Institutions, Telangana, India

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science & Engineering

September 2020

August 2024